<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Writings on Yannis Rizos</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/</link><description>Recent content in Writings on Yannis Rizos</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 02:16:25 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yrizos.com/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Two Hours to Find a Swapped String</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/two-hours-to-find-a-swapped-string/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 02:16:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/two-hours-to-find-a-swapped-string/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Early in my career, I landed a job where I was finally writing production code that mattered. The company had an ERP system and an e-commerce platform, and needed them to communicate with each other. My job was to build the integration layer that would keep product data flowing between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The requirements seemed straightforward enough. The ERP would send product information, my system would translate it, and the store would receive it. Both systems used product codes to identify items, and since those codes looked like ordinary strings, I treated them as ordinary strings. That&amp;rsquo;s what the rest of the codebase did, and it felt like the natural choice.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Super Secret Project That Probably Won’t Happen</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/super-secret-project-that-probably-wont-happen/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/super-secret-project-that-probably-wont-happen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In May 2023, I sent an email to a handful of engineers inviting them to discuss a “&lt;em&gt;super secret project that probably won’t happen&lt;/em&gt;.” Yes, that was the actual meeting title. I figured if I was asking people to bet time on something uncertain, I should at least be honest about the odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25 mentorship pairs later, that meeting turned into the most unexpectedly durable thing I’ve built at Epignosis. I’m still not entirely sure why it worked.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>From Ancient Theater to Modern Hackathlon</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/from-ancient-theater-to-modern-hackathlon/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/from-ancient-theater-to-modern-hackathlon/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That single word captures everything after 3 days at the {Re}Solve Hackathon by Open at the Thessaloniki International Fair 2025. The kind that comes from being fully present, from watching builders turn ideas into working prototypes, and from seeing teams create things they had not thought possible. The tiredness felt earned, interesting, fun, and at times humbling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My alarm went off at 6 am on Friday. I arrived at the airport by 7:30 am, landed in Thessaloniki at 9:30 am, and entered the venue by 10:15 am. By Sunday night, I was back home in Athens. A whirlwind weekend of a thousand freddo espressos. And I was there only to observe and guide. I can’t even begin to imagine how the actual builders felt.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Into the Codebase, One Bug at a Time</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/into-the-codebase-one-bug-at-a-time/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 23:49:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/into-the-codebase-one-bug-at-a-time/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The temple was crumbling. I could see that much walking in. No clear maps. No reliable guides. Just a system that worked well enough that no one had bothered to document where the traps were hidden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking over a new team means making choices about what comes first. Most leaders push for quick wins. Ship a feature. Show value. Build momentum. I did the opposite. I told the team we were stopping feature work for an entire sprint. We would fix bugs, pay down technical debt, and repair what was broken.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The End of Coding as We Know It</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/the-end-of-coding-as-we-know-it/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 22:48:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/the-end-of-coding-as-we-know-it/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In 1839, Louis Daguerre’s invention, the daguerreotype, was unveiled to the world as a gift from France to humanity. Imagine how incredible this must have seemed back then. It captured people’s imaginations because it could produce a lifelike image in minutes. Painters had spent centuries perfecting realism, but suddenly, a machine could do it better and faster. If a machine could capture reality perfectly, then what was left for artists to do? People genuinely wondered if painting would become obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Slow Productivity</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/slow-productivity/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 19:39:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/slow-productivity/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Cal Newport’s book &lt;em&gt;Slow Productivity: The Lost Art of Accomplishment Without Burnout&lt;/em&gt; invites readers to rethink how they work. He challenges the relentless pursuit of efficiency and productivity by advocating for a slower, more deliberate approach. Newport encourages doing fewer tasks, working at a natural pace, and prioritising quality. While these ideas resonate, the execution of the book falls flat in several ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="key-themes-of-slow-productivity"&gt;Key Themes of Slow Productivity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newport critiques the “cult of pseudo-productivity,” where busywork and shallow tasks dominate workplaces. He argues this mindset leads to burnout and diminished output quality, particularly in knowledge work. The book draws heavily on historical figures like Jane Austen, Benjamin Franklin, and John McPhee to illustrate how deliberate pacing can lead to meaningful accomplishments.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Nostromo Incident</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/the-nostromo-incident/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 23:44:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/the-nostromo-incident/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-nostromo-incident-a-seven-whys-root-causeanalysis"&gt;The Nostromo Incident: A Seven Whys Root Cause Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ridley Scott’s &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt; is a masterpiece of sci-fi horror. It is terrifying, suspenseful, and brilliantly crafted. Beneath the xenomorph and the visceral body horror, it shows what happens when a corporation sends people into danger without telling them the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When disasters happen, the obvious answer rarely explains what went wrong. The 7 whys technique keeps asking why until the real problem emerges. Each answer reveals another layer. The seventh reveals the root.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Learning to Ride, Learning to Lead</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/learning-to-ride-learning-to-lead/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 12:14:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/learning-to-ride-learning-to-lead/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Watching my daughter learn to ride a bike was a mix of teetering starts and bursts of confidence, like the time she wobbled forward a few metres, only to tumble onto the soft grass, laughing despite the fall. It wasn’t just about teaching her to balance and pedal. It was about helping her see what she could do once she started trusting herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It started with a balance bike. My wife insisted on getting one. I was skeptical. Balance bikes didn’t exist when I was growing up. We learned on bikes with training wheels, leaning the wrong way, and developing bad habits that had to be unlearned later. The balance bike seemed too simple, almost like skipping a step.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Blood, Sweat, and Pixels</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/blood-sweat-and-pixels/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 21:53:21 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/blood-sweat-and-pixels/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;”Oh, Jason,” one developer said. “It’s a miracle that any game is made.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason Schreier’s &lt;em&gt;Blood, Sweat, and Pixels&lt;/em&gt; pulls back the curtain on the chaotic, often heart-wrenching world of video game development. As a software developer and avid gamer, I was captivated by the stories of passion and struggle that define the industry. Through meticulous interviews and in-depth reporting, Schreier documents the journeys of beloved games like &lt;em&gt;Stardew Valley&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Witcher 3&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dragon Age: Inquisition&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Diablo III&lt;/em&gt;. Each chapter offers a rare, insider’s perspective on the immense challenges developers face, from technical hurdles to publisher demands, while navigating the crushing reality of “crunch” culture.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Where Do You Do Your Best Thinking?</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/where-do-you-do-your-best-thinking/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 12:09:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/where-do-you-do-your-best-thinking/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I finished reading Gabrielle Zevin’s &lt;em&gt;Tomorrow, and Tomorrow, and Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt; on a Saturday morning in October. I had been carrying the final chapter on my old Kindle for 2 weeks, finding reasons to delay. The story deserved better than a rushed ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forest was quiet that morning except for the wind moving through pine branches and the occasional distant shout from where the children were learning below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every other Saturday, my daughter attends environmental consciousness classes at the Hymettus Forest. She learns through play, discovering how to care for nature, herself, and her group. What began as her educational experience has grown into a meaningful ritual for both of us.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Mars Rover Challenge in Rust: Houston, Do You Copy?</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/the-mars-rover-challenge-in-rust-houston-do-you-copy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 11:59:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/the-mars-rover-challenge-in-rust-houston-do-you-copy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our rover navigation system is ready for its maiden voyage, but first, it needs to know where to go! The mission parameters have provided specific test scenarios to validate our implementation. My rover needs to interpret these commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"&gt;&lt;code class="language-plaintext" data-lang="plaintext"&gt;&lt;span style="display:flex;"&gt;&lt;span&gt;5 5
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="display:flex;"&gt;&lt;span&gt;1 2 N
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="display:flex;"&gt;&lt;span&gt;LMLMLMLMM
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="display:flex;"&gt;&lt;span&gt;3 3 E
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="display:flex;"&gt;&lt;span&gt;MMRMMRMRRM
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;And respond with precise positional data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"&gt;&lt;code class="language-plaintext" data-lang="plaintext"&gt;&lt;span style="display:flex;"&gt;&lt;span&gt;1 3 N
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="display:flex;"&gt;&lt;span&gt;5 1 E
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 id="establishing-communication-receiving-user-input"&gt;Establishing Communication: Receiving User Input&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first challenge was creating a communication channel with Mission Control. I turned to Rust&amp;rsquo;s powerful &lt;code&gt;std::io&lt;/code&gt; module to establish this vital link:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Mars Rover Challenge in Rust: Let's Get Moving!</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/the-mars-rover-challenge-in-rust-lets-get-moving/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 11:52:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/the-mars-rover-challenge-in-rust-lets-get-moving/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Now that the challenge is clear, it&amp;rsquo;s time to start coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To kick things off, I got my project set up using Cargo – nothing fancy, just the basics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"&gt;&lt;span style="display:flex;"&gt;&lt;span&gt;cargo new mars-rover-rust
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="display:flex;"&gt;&lt;span&gt;cd mars-rover-rust
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 id="charting-the-course-defining-directions"&gt;Charting the Course: Defining Directions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First up, I needed to figure out how our little rover would know which way it&amp;rsquo;s facing. I went with the classics here – good old North, East, South, and West. Here&amp;rsquo;s how I set that up in Rust:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Mars Rover Challenge in Rust: Setting the Scene</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/the-mars-rover-challenge-in-rust-setting-the-scene/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 11:52:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/the-mars-rover-challenge-in-rust-setting-the-scene/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As a Rust beginner, I was looking for a project that would both teach me the language fundamentals and keep me engaged. The Mars Rover Challenge fits perfectly - it&amp;rsquo;s an intriguing problem that simulates robotic exploration of Mars while introducing key programming concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="setting-the-scene"&gt;Setting the Scene&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine controlling rovers tasked with exploring the Martian terrain. These rovers need to navigate a rectangular plateau while sending visual data back to Earth. The challenge involves translating simple commands into precise rover movements, and dealing with positioning, orientation, and grid-based navigation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Setting Up Visual Studio Code for Rust on macOS</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/setting-up-visual-studio-code-for-rust-on-macos/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 11:50:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/setting-up-visual-studio-code-for-rust-on-macos/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Setting up Visual Studio Code for Rust development is quick and straightforward. While I prefer PHPStorm for larger projects, VS Code is perfect for smaller ones. It’s fast, lightweight, and just works. For this guide, I’m assuming you already have &lt;a href="https://dev.to/yrizos/installing-rust-on-macos-with-homebrew-51fk"&gt;Rust installed via Homebrew&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-1-grab-vs-code"&gt;Step 1: Grab VS Code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Head over to &lt;a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/"&gt;code.visualstudio.com&lt;/a&gt; and download VS Code. Follow the installation instructions provided for MacOS to set it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="step-2-create-a-hello-world-project-with-cargo"&gt;Step 2: Create a Hello World Project with cargo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Terminal and create a new Rust project:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Installing Rust on macOS with Homebrew</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/installing-rust-on-macos-with-homebrew/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 09:28:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/installing-rust-on-macos-with-homebrew/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This Sunday, I had a bit of extra time, so I decided to brush up on &lt;a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;. Whether you are a seasoned developer or just starting out, getting your tools set up is always the first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Rust’s official installation tool, &lt;code&gt;rustup&lt;/code&gt;, is excellent and versatile, I prefer using &lt;a href="https://brew.sh/"&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; whenever possible. It is simple, familiar, and keeps everything neatly managed in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="step-1-install-rust"&gt;Step 1: Install Rust&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Launch the terminal and run the following command to install Rust:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>