<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Engineering-Leadership on Yannis Rizos</title><link>https://yrizos.com/tags/engineering-leadership/</link><description>Recent content in Engineering-Leadership on Yannis Rizos</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yrizos.com/tags/engineering-leadership/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Super Secret Project That Probably Won’t Happen</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/super-secret-project-that-probably-wont-happen/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/super-secret-project-that-probably-wont-happen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In May 2023, I sent an email to a handful of engineers inviting them to discuss a “&lt;em&gt;super secret project that probably won’t happen&lt;/em&gt;.” Yes, that was the actual meeting title. I figured if I was asking people to bet time on something uncertain, I should at least be honest about the odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25 mentorship pairs later, that meeting turned into the most unexpectedly durable thing I’ve built at Epignosis. I’m still not entirely sure why it worked.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Into the Codebase, One Bug at a Time</title><link>https://yrizos.com/writing/into-the-codebase-one-bug-at-a-time/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 23:49:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/writing/into-the-codebase-one-bug-at-a-time/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The temple was crumbling. I could see that much walking in. No clear maps. No reliable guides. Just a system that worked well enough that no one had bothered to document where the traps were hidden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking over a new team means making choices about what comes first. Most leaders push for quick wins. Ship a feature. Show value. Build momentum. I did the opposite. I told the team we were stopping feature work for an entire sprint. We would fix bugs, pay down technical debt, and repair what was broken.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>What We Learned Building AI Features for TalentLMS</title><link>https://yrizos.com/speaking/ai-features-talentlms/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 19:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/speaking/ai-features-talentlms/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The first &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/mindstone-athens-practicalai-meetup/"&gt;Mindstone Athens Practical AI Meetup&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="https://www.epignosishq.com/"&gt;Epignosis HQ&lt;/a&gt; drew a full house. It was the opening event of the Athens chapter of the Global Mindstone Practical AI community, and the energy in the room matched that sense of beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My talk focused on the gap between getting an LLM to produce decent output and delivering something that can serve 25 million users. The distance between those two points is filled with the kind of engineering problems that don’t show up in demos. APIs fail at random, costs can spiral over a weekend, and teams need systems they can maintain without losing their minds.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Breaking Down the Monolith</title><link>https://yrizos.com/speaking/breaking-down-the-monolith/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 10:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://yrizos.com/speaking/breaking-down-the-monolith/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Athens Megaron International Conference Center is an imposing place. Walking into it that morning felt like stepping into a different league. It was my first time presenting to a large audience, and we had no idea what to expect. Five minutes before the session started, the room was already packed. People were standing along the walls and at the back, trying to find a spot. It was equal parts exhilarating and nerve-racking.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>